Welcome to the lecture about Security in Operating
Systems.
You can find here the reading instructions
for this lecture. Most of the material is
covered in these slides, while other parts
are for you to read directly from the book.
We are going to begin this lecture with an
introduction and overview of what security
is (in the context of Operating Systems),
we will then cover the topic of Protection
Domains and have a look at both Access Control
Lists and Capabilities. We will then discuss
Authentication and finally cover a very well-known
way of exploiting software bugs: buffer overflow
attacks.
Let’s start with our overview.
We all know that the information we access
and store in our computer is being moved across
different devices, like the disk, the main
memory, the network card, and so on.
We also know that the operating system has
a key role in deciding how this information
is being moved.
It is of course clear that part of this information
is important and/or sensitive: your passwords,
your credit card number, and so on
and we can imagine attackers might be interested
in accessing such information. Something important
to notice here is that such wish to access
information is not limited to reading the
information, someone might want to alter it
(to pretend you said something in a mail you
did not) or just prevent you (the real owner
of such information) from accessing it (so
that you cannot recover all your files if
you do not pay a ransom for them).
Unfortunately for us, the software we use
(including the operating system’s one) is
full of bugs. Security bugs, called vulnerabilities,
are often used by attackers to inject special
input (exploit) that allows them, in a way
or another, to fulfill their malicious intentions.
At this point, it is important to realize
that one additional trade-off we have in the
context of Operating Systems is that of feature-rich
software versus simple and secure software.
We tend to like systems with a lot of tools,
gadgets, and features, but the truth is that
the more of these we get, the higher the chances
that a bug can be used against us.
If you take the very simple example about
mails, you probably agree with me that the
possibility of sending images and files is
something we prefer over the possibility of
sending only plain text.
But we have to acknowledge that it is hard
for the attacker to gain control of a system
through simple text, while it is significantly
easier if executable files can be shared via
mail.
At this point, I want to stress that the topic
of security is a very broad and complicated
one, and this lecture does not aim at covering
all aspects of it, of course.
If we focus on the type of attacks and security
threats that exist, we can list (among others),
worms: freestanding programs that can propagate
through various computers without user intervention,
viruses, which on the other hand will attach
to files and programs and will propagate depending
on how users interact with infected files
and programs, trojan horses, malware disguised
as legitimate software, Denial of Service
and Distributed Denial of Service attacks,
and so on...
If we focus on the concept of "victim", we
must note that being a victim of a security
incident does not imply the attacker is after
you or your data, the attacker might be using
you to achieve his or her goals.
In this lecture, we will only focus on some
security aspects that concern the Operating
System.
More concretely, we will focus on
confidentiality, which is about keeping secret
data secret or ensuring data is accessed only
by authorized people,
integrity, which is about ensuring data is
modified only by authorized persons,
and availability, which is about ensuring
no one can disturb the system and make it
unusable.
As you can imagine, these are not the only
security aspects one can think about, but
we will not cover additional ones.
Something worth mentioning here is that we
often hear the term hacker used to refer to
malicious attackers.
In reality, a hacker only refers to someone
with excellent programming skills. We can
differentiate between white hats, who try
to attack a system and develop security tools
to make such a system more secure, and black
hats, who on the other hand use the same tools
(and hence the expression dual use) with malicious
intentions.
It is also worth mentioning that attacks can
be classified along different dimensions.
They could be differentiated between passive
and active ones, for instance.
In practice, there’s no silver bullet to
handle all security aspects. We usually end
up using a combination of various techniques,
including cryptography, software hardening
(which we will cover later), and even more
(Intel SGX is an interesting example of a
recent approach, which is currently a hot
research topic).
Security practitioners usually talk of trusted
rather than secure systems. A trusted system
is a system that has formally stated security
requirements that it meets. For a system to
be trusted, we usually need to identify the
Trusted Computing Base, so the portion of
hardware, kernel, and user processes with
root-level access that can affect security.
Such portion should be kept as small as possible,
to make it easier to maintain it.
Once we have our TCB, we need a model that
specifies what should be protected, who can
do what, and what type of adversary we can
deal with (his/her power, basically) and make
sure all system calls are checked by a so-called
reference monitor before entering/operating
in the TCB.